<rss xmlns:dc="https://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="https://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Alex Mahrou - projected.xyz</title><description>if it can be measured, it can be improved</description><link>https://projected.xyz/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 19:33:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://projected.xyz/author/alex/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>A follow on to: Why So many data scientists are leaving their jobs (TL;DR, only the entitled ones do)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Jonny Brooks-Bartlett's article, &lt;a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/why-so-many-data-scientists-are-leaving-their-jobs-a1f0329d7ea4"&gt;Why so many Data Scientists are leaving their jobs&lt;/a&gt;, inspired me to write this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree wholeheartedly with Jonny's summation of expectations vs reality of the data science job. Furthermore, I believe folks are leaving because they &lt;em&gt;idealistically&lt;/em&gt; think that the &lt;strong&gt;expectation &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; match the reality&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To preface this, I'd like to state that data science is booming and many are new to it. I come to this table having had over a decade of experience in Geographic Information Systems (GIS). Many lessons learned from my career apply here. From the get-go, as an undergrad research assistant in 2004, I had the pleasure of my first data project, where I needed to digitize 10's of 1000's of bicycle trip segments on a map from paper and digital field collected user-survey data, assign linear reference to them (m-values), store them in a database, then deliver them in a web browser to the end user, using a web mapping technology called ArcIMS. Ever since this first project, I've been in the business of delivering data over the web in one form or another, from paginated reports, dynamic charts, and (of course) slippy maps (like google maps). So that's my claim to tell you that I've been here for a little bit, and hopefully you'll take my opinions here seriously. I don't know it all, but I've been here long enough to know where things usually fall flat and don't succeed when it comes to a project that delivers data. But first and foremost, these are just my opinions based on my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our First Jobs introduce us to the broom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;-Andrew Carnegie&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Carnegie, who's wealth equated to 2.1% of the US GDP at his time, puts it best. Just because it's the sexiest job of the 21t century, doesn't mean you're entitled to the sexiest parts of the gig. Things are sloppy, awkward, unorganized, and disheveled-- you need practice to make it better (I'm talking data science btw). ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's reference the 1974 thesis of Roger Tomlinson-- the late great geographer of our time. I went ahead and filled in modern buzzwords on his diagram. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/03/roger.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I head up a data science SaaS product, and guess what? Data Scientist isn't a role on my internal team (but it is a role). Fundamentally, data gets gathered, then handled, THEN ANALYZED, THEN DECISIONS ARE MADE. You can't just swoop in on the &lt;em&gt;analyzed or decisions being made part&lt;/em&gt;. Data science is a &lt;strong&gt;team sport&lt;/strong&gt; and will require &lt;strong&gt;domain knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Shame on anyone who takes a gig and assumes that it's their job to walk down the already paved road of data science pulling a cart full of insights to make any given company more profitable and competitive-- they need to have their head checked. There are a few industries where you can walk in, but outside of this, you're going to have to be realistic about the nature of the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="theteamsport"&gt;The Team Sport&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's break down the roles on my team. This is just an example, and not all roles have to necessarily be one person each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; She's got a ton of SQL (language, not software) skills, she can move data from place to place. She builds a smart data pipeline. That means proper CRUD methods instead of lazy ETL. Going to the data, instead of forklifting the data over to you. Setting up even-driven triggers on changes in the data to further feed the pipeline. She builds performant views that ensure fast queries downstream that are made against the data. That means that algorithms and statistical packages as they relate to the domain of the data science problems need to be front-of-mind here. That means getting outside of one's comfort zone to learn about the "business" behind your existence. Only then, can she begin to apply the sexy bits of data science. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front-end developer:&lt;/strong&gt; For our product, Data science is delivered to the masses in a browser. So, this guy needs to understand working with JavaScript and HTML. Good chops in security and methods for dealing with multitenancy help as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DevOps Engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; Servers, services, cloud technology, performance benchmarking, network architecture, patches, and security. She makes sure that the trains run on time. The devops engineer provides the canvas for everyone to paint on. &lt;em&gt;Could&lt;/em&gt; be used interchangeably with IT, but just don't expect this person to be looking after your Outlook server. This person is seconded to the data science team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now here's where things get interesting. What tools / technology you use will dictate if you need this next role. If you use a self-service data tool like Qlik, Tableau, MicroStrategy, etc., you probably won't need this next role. HOWEVER, if you intend to do something truly original, you'll need this person. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Visualization Engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; This guy is constantly talking to the end customer or product manager to determine what people need to see. How do tables need to be formatted? What kind of maps or charts, and visualizations need to be displayed in the browser? Then this person uses skills in D3.js, or other modern visualization libraries to deliver the last mile. He'll have to work closely with the data engineer and the front-end dev roles as well to ensure data integrity and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team Leader / Product Manager:&lt;/strong&gt;
She's the glue that keeps the team together. Constant communication between team members, stakeholders, and end-clients is key here. To ensure that solutions that are delivered get used, and that there's a feedback loop of continuous improvement from the users back to the sprints that create the product features. She needs to have a shallow (that's OK) understanding of data science techniques and approaches. She's the coach on the team that'll be able to articulate complex topics between owner's box (executives &amp;amp; clients) and the players (the team). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="thedomainiswherethesciencehappens"&gt;The Domain is where the science happens&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The End User is my "data scientist":&lt;/strong&gt; This person delivers the last mile of data science (per Roger Tomlinson's thesis. This person might already be a scientist. In my case, it's environmental scientists and subject matter experts. They fill the roles of the data scientist here. They know what they need from the data already. They've had to deal with running statistics in Excel for years or they've fumbled through Access databases to try and get their jobs done. They don't need a multidisciplinary college-educated data scientist to swoop in and tell them how to do their jobs or tell them what to glean from their data, they just need a better way to deliver this. There are complex statistical packages in R that are academically tied to the domain that these folks are salivating to deliver in the browser, but they educate us on the applicability, not the other way around. This leads me a bold claim....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are no "data scientists" on my payroll&lt;/strong&gt;. Jonny's article speaks to a bigger problem in data science. The person who might identify with what he's talking about might be a "trained data scientist", who's been schooled in narrowly focused academic python/r exercises, tensorflow, hadoop, or (I hope not) an off-the-shelf drag-n-drop tools like tableau or Power BI. The data science that everyone romanticizes about with virally-awesome visualizations, machine learning, neural networks, and artificial intelligence is built on the blood, sweat, and tears of the un-sexy fundamental work of the aforementioned roles. You're not going to walk into a gig and deliver these things at scale unless an organization is ready and worthy. It's a team sport, and it's a tough curve to climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most immediate applicable data science programs are domain-specific-- think bioinformatics, or quantitative finance. In many cases a different program will take your money, "make you a data scientist", and turn you into a shallow multi-disciplinary generalist-- people are jumping into this field and now there's masses of people armed with solutions who have very little interest in REALLY defining the problems embedded deep in a domain. Thus, that's why we're seeing many people ever-still in-search in this field. They believe they're entitled to the sexy bits, and they think it'll exist in an organization that's "ready to hire our first data scientist!". Most organizations are still climbing the unsexy curve of data management, data governance, and data quality. Sorry bud, you've come from the future, armed with your Coursera Jupyter notebook machine-learning chops: You need to cool it, and understand that to get to that point, you need to slog through the tough truths of what it takes to build a culture of data science. Start with the unsexy fundamentals (the broom), learn about the business of your business, be patient, and eventually, hopefully not alone, you'll create something amazing. If this bores you, then you probably just need to seek a job in academia/university, where you can get paid to simulate and research real-world problems with data science while the real-world catches up.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2018/03/31/only-lazy-data-scientists-are-leaving-their-jobs/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">cd952c2a-67cd-43ce-8bfb-e6a1ac079f70</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 19:32:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ArcGIS Identity Crisis Part 3</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm not one to complain without a solution, and the previous blog post &lt;a href="https://projected.xyz/2018/03/03/the-arcgis-identity-crisis-part-two/"&gt;The ArcGIS Identity Crisis Part Two&lt;/a&gt;, was kind of left open-ended. Some might have walked away thinking, "Oh so Alex wants everything for free, huh?". Not necessarily. I hope that folks at Esri are listening. My beef is on two fronts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, Why introduce more middleware betweent the data tier and the web display? What used to be just ArcGIS Server and a Reverse Proxy (for on-prem) is now ArcGIS Server, a &lt;strong&gt;Mandatory Portal Installation&lt;/strong&gt;, and a web adapter. This day-and-age, companies &lt;em&gt;should be&lt;/em&gt; striving to pare down middleware, bloat, and create less administrivia for security. This has achieved quite the opposite. I don't see this getting any slimmer. In recent product announcements, they’re just making it easier to orchestrate the install of this bloat via Jupyter notebooks and/or chef automation. No thanks. Speed eating is still eating too much. Regardless if it's at speed. The bloat persists.
&lt;div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:56%;position:relative;"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/11KBpBvcLG1xWU" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/this-is-hot-97-11KBpBvcLG1xWU"&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;second&lt;/strong&gt; beef is with the lack of options for licensing based outside of the named user. Look at Tableau Server or Power Bi. Both compete, and both are models of different licensing options. Tableau is the best parallel you can draw to ArcGIS in this sense because they are pushing the named user model. However, Tableau &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; offer an unlimited option for named users in a commercial capacity with one 8 core server. ArcGIS does not. What's their answer? More portals! Portals for your portals, that are connected via portal-to-portal connections! Go forth and sell your client some of our portals. &lt;br&gt;
Power BI licensing is even better and more flexible than Tableau, they outright support their integrators and commercial partners and state as such in their channel 9 videos/docs, and show you exactly how you can license and deploy as a for profit consultancy their Power BI embedded solution. Just purchase the computing capacity and off-you-go. Literally, pay for renders per hour! &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/03/PowerBIPricing.PNG" alt=""&gt;
I've come to gather that confidence in one’s product as a vendor is directly correlated to the pricing model. Unless your ubiquitous (Salesforce) or a specialized/focused tool (think Fulcrum), named users translate into very little confidence, whereas pricing on capacity, consumption, and renders, translates into the utmost confidence in your product. Named user is this context is a way to achieve your revenue dreams!: With a crutch, plain and simple. They thrive on the fact that you pay for a year’s worth of service, and you might or might not use the tool-- not their problem! They've been paid. It doesn't take a seasoned Silicon Valley pro to understand that there are metrics like &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; usage of the tool that they're collecting on their end, that they are disincentivized to share with you with the named-user model. &lt;a href="https://blog.popcornmetrics.com/5-user-engagement-metrics-for-growth/"&gt;Google it, why not be transparent and free up these metrics for us to see in our subscriptions?&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solutions Anyone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I doubt the bloat of Portal will be slimed down anytime soon, I do know that a mechanism exists within the ArcGIS Product to bill on consumption. They do it right now with their premium services like routing. What's so backwards is &lt;a href="https://www.arcgis.com/apps/Directions/resources/doc/addpremiumservice.html"&gt;that they allow you to configure &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; premium services for anonymous access&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/03/routing.PNG" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, great let me just use this nifty resource proxy and app login mechanism for my own app and secure services! &lt;strong&gt;NOT!&lt;/strong&gt; Only Esri can do that. It's against the rules, they must pass through the named user toll booth. See below, the first green outline, it can't be private content. Second green circle, it must be public content-- as if there was ever an in between situation. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/03/tos.PNG" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In summary&lt;/strong&gt;, I'm done trying to get a vendor to see the light here, and that they could celebrate an all-of-the-above scenario by just offering metered-secured access to the services that people spin up themselves. They are just shooting themselves in the foot by trying to push portals and middleware instead. 
&lt;div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:69%;position:relative;"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/bYekqm1pBL3RC" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/family-guy-wordplay-acute-bYekqm1pBL3RC"&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;I do know one thing,&lt;/strong&gt; developers just want to create cool apps, not be a recruitment arm for subscriptions for a vendor-- and even more so, neither do fresh college grads. These are uncomfortable conversations between the developer and the end user that are likened to selling Advocare, Herbal Life, or Amway. &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all apps are public, or only suited to level 1 named users inside of an organization. A large chunk of us are B2B, we build stuff in the real world, we consult for a living, we're the ones who actually support projects that build pipelines, bridges, roads, tunnels, remediate superfund sites, and clean up the environment. There's a private factor there to our WIP that will always span many stakeholders in many organizations. And yes, we the people who pour our blood sweat and tears into the trenches cleaning data, mapping, creating models and applying the scientific research to our client's issues won't stand for a named user transaction while we attempt to share our challenging work with our clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This speaks to a bigger issue in technology, that I intend to write about later. When you're creating on someone else’s stack you're just riffing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Being an &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ESRI?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#ESRI&lt;/a&gt; integrator is like being a cover band.  You might really jam on “Living on a Prayer” and tweek it a bit to fit your style but in the end, you’re locked into someone else’s IP and decisions&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; FOSS4G BlackBloc 👨‍👦👨🏼‍💻🏔🥃 (@Spatial_Punk) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Spatial_Punk/status/977203596050780160?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 23, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Peter Theil takes it home in his book ZERO TO ONE:&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we think about the future, we hope for a future of progress. That progress can take one of two forms. Horizontal or extensive progress means copying things that work—going from 1 to n. &lt;strong&gt;Horizontal progress&lt;/strong&gt; is easy to imagine because we already know what it looks like. Vertical or intensive progress means doing new things—going from 0 to 1. Vertical progress is harder to imagine because it requires doing something nobody else has ever done. If you take one typewriter and build 100, you have made horizontal progress. If you have a typewriter and build a word processor, you have made &lt;strong&gt;vertical progress&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why just remix something that's already been done? You think these vendors &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; give a damn about your skills? They want scalps (named users), and I hate you break it to you, yours is just as valuable as the next guy's or gal’s. They want you to sharpen your skills "just far enough" to be dangerous within the confines of their walled garden-- while they collect more data, understand more markets, applications, and slowly but surely marginalize the power user to one of a Homer Simpson (if you're lucky) who job it is to carry a proud title, and be a lighthouse within your organization for more scalps. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style="width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:76%;position:relative;"&gt;&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/xT5LMM4XqfaSMQcKAM" width="100%" height="100%" style="position:absolute" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/season-8-the-simpsons-8x23-xT5LMM4XqfaSMQcKAM"&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a world where we want instant gratification, give me a low barrier to entry &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt;, low license cost, &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. Then I can just push buttons and not have to worry about learning something harder. Don't fall into this trap. Do some arithmetic. Take the subscription cost that a vendor might be pushing on you and it's &lt;em&gt;apparent&lt;/em&gt; convenience, multiply it three or five years out (don't forget to multiply the named users too!), now go back and see that it's not that hard to justify investing in yourself or the right people to achieve your dreams of creating something amazing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2018/03/24/arcgis-identity-crisis-part-3-a-new-hope/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7ceb0283-8e3f-463f-ba51-f48c7e076094</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 04:31:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This is a tribute to Who I follow in GIS, Data, and Life</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Below is a list of folks who make the biggest impact for me. It aint all about technology. ;-). I tend to list folks here that CREATE content and conversation. While I follow many people, those that tend to make an impact are those who just don't retweet something we already know. News has been commoditized folks, give me your raw opinions and creations. You make the most impact with everyone as a creator of things, not a reporter of things that we've ALREADY received through the media firehose. The folks below are truly original. Below is my brief tribute to them and a description of why they have my attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Spatial_Punk"&gt;Spatial punk | Todd Barr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
is the little voice in your head for geospatial telling you that there's a better way to do things. He frustrates me from time to time, and that's a good thing. He's the shock jock of GIS, and proud of it. His rants on using proprietary tech are a gut punch for many working in Geospatial, as you'd have to live under a rock not to at least occasionally be forced into working with proprietary formats and software. What separates him from other folks who might come across as elitist when it comes to toolsets? He's not smug, he's not beneath a public conversation. Where others will err on the side of caution from a public debate, he'll dive right in. He's also a truly universal dude. He takes on his super hero form because he feels like he must for the sake of all of us. And I'm grateful for it. Here's a little nugget from this week:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Time for my weekly FU.  If you haven&amp;#39; t even experimented with Spatial SQL with an enterprisish database, then you are A) Selling yourself short B) won&amp;#39;t get a job outside of the ESRI ecosystem&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; FOSS4G BlackBloc 👨‍👦👨🏼‍💻🏔🥃 (@Spatial_Punk) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Spatial_Punk/status/972240753815506944?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 9, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHoliday"&gt;Ryan Holiday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; introduced me to stoic philosophy. His books are the biggest secret to my career and approach to life. When you take on the advice from the stories laid out in his books, you'll feel unstoppable-- and he aint no Tony Robbins (and that's a good thing). I read every single one of Ryan Holiday's books-- and listen to them too, because he narrates ALL OF THEM. The Obstacle is the Way was the first: My absolute favorite. I don't listen to music in my car. I Bluetooth my phone and plug in Ryan Holiday on my commute. One day we'll look back at the philosophers of &lt;strong&gt;our&lt;/strong&gt; age, and Ryan Holiday will be at the top of the list. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&amp;quot;When you become a craftsman in a world of carpenters, you will stand out and people will clamor to work with you.” Jon Gordon&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ryan Holiday (@RyanHoliday) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHoliday/status/971860683120881664?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/levelsio"&gt;Pieter Levels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Creator of Nomad List and Hood maps, and others. Pieter is THE digital nomad. Follow him to truly understand less-is-more startup philosophy when it comes to technology. One of his websites, that makes him close to 50K per month (at the time of writing this) is running on a few php scripts. He's also extremely humble and extremely transparent as to the recipe that got him there. From time to time, I get a kick out of how pedantic developers will reach out to him, and try to instruct him on a "better" way to do something. If they could only understand that Pieter makes more money in three months than they probably do in an entire year. But he'd never remind them that. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;.&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/LukasValatka?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@LukasValatka&lt;/a&gt; I have 0% passion for programming the right way, I have lots of passion for making things tho, code is just a means to an end&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pieter Levels 🏝 (@levelsio) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/levelsio/status/695733323847573504?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;February 5, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DrexelPooja"&gt;Pooja Gandhi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 1/2 of the data duo-- A blog that pits two Tableau zen masters against each other to produce the most beautiful and impactful data visualizations that you can imagine, spanning a myriad of topics. Her work is truly inspirational for providing a feedstock of ideas for my day job where I'd try to create beautiful and functional visualizations in Tableau that might someday hold a candle to her work product. Here's an example below of her work. 
&lt;div class="tableauPlaceholder" id="viz1520698876556" style="position: relative"&gt;&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href="https://projected.xyz/#"&gt;&lt;img alt="The victims of the 21st-century slave trade  " src="https://&amp;/#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;Wo&amp;#47;WorldTrafficking&amp;#47;WorldTrafficking&amp;#47;1_rss.png" style="border: none"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;&lt;object class="tableauViz" style="display:none;"&gt;&lt;param name="host_url" value="https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2F"&gt; &lt;param name="embed_code_version" value="3"&gt; &lt;param name="site_root" value=""&gt;&lt;param name="name" value="WorldTrafficking&amp;#47;WorldTrafficking"&gt;&lt;param name="tabs" value="no"&gt;&lt;param name="toolbar" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="static_image" value="https:&amp;#47;&amp;#47;public.tableau.com&amp;#47;static&amp;#47;images&amp;#47;Wo&amp;#47;WorldTrafficking&amp;#47;WorldTrafficking&amp;#47;1.png"&gt; &lt;param name="animate_transition" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="display_static_image" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="display_spinner" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="display_overlay" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="display_count" value="yes"&gt;&lt;param name="showTabs" value="y"&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;                &lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;                    var divElement = document.getElementById('viz1520698876556');                    var vizElement = divElement.getElementsByTagName('object')[0];                    vizElement.style.width='925px';vizElement.style.height='727px';                    var scriptElement = document.createElement('script');                    scriptElement.src = '&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js"&gt;https://public.tableau.com/javascripts/api/viz_v1.js&lt;/a&gt;';                    vizElement.parentNode.insertBefore(scriptElement, vizElement);                &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nusr_ett"&gt;Saltbae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Why do I follow this crazy butcher/meat master turned-internet-legend? Because he resonates one thing for me: discipline and determination. He had humble beginnings, and he keeps up his practice. Be like Saltbae in everything you do. Keep practicing, soon your muscles will form memory, and you'll be kicking ass before you know it on things you once thought impossible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-video" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="und" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/saltbae?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#saltbae&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/ibxA1xqOfu"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ibxA1xqOfu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nusret #saltbae (@nusr_ett) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nusr_ett/status/965240323906703360?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;February 18, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NadiehBremer"&gt;Nadieh Bremer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; creates stunning, award winning, visualizations. Follow her to understand true creativity at work coupled with the technical fortitude necessary to deliver in visualizations in their most native form. She's a d3.js ninja. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Always like it when mistakes turn into interesting outcomes :) &lt;a href="https://t.co/1vkNHNsaLw"&gt;pic.twitter.com/1vkNHNsaLw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nadieh Bremer (@NadiehBremer) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NadiehBremer/status/970073080151277568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;in conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;, that's it! There are others, but these folks have my attention. They're truly inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2018/03/10/this-is-a-tribute-who-i-follow-in-gis-data-and-life/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b16a7505-a6d8-443b-a09c-f30c47319575</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 18:15:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The ArcGIS Identity Crisis Part Two</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back in August of 2016,&lt;/strong&gt; I published a post entitled "The ArcGIS Identity Crisis". I was frustrated with the direction of the product with named users. Little did I know that after publishing this post, so many folks shared my same frustrations. &lt;a href="https://projected.xyz/2016/08/06/the-arcgis-identity-crisis/"&gt;The ArcGIS Identity Crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might have had a hand in turning the tides to eventually get Esri to change their licensing to allow for unlimited level one users in Portal a year later. It's hard to say. But this change has been good for lots of folks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there's still a dilemma. Why can't we publish to ArcGIS Server directly to Pro? The explanation as to the incentives for Esri not to do so are crystal clear if you keep reading. As I write this, Esri Business Partners and Developers are headed to palm springs for the 2018 Esri Partner Conference and Dev Summit. If you're headed there this week, go look in the mirror and understand your business model as it relates to this tech, then ask yourself how might the product direction of this vendor begin to affect your bottom line in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I see with the product direction, they've released ArcGIS Pro years ago. Presumably on the premises that you now get better 3D! 64 Bit too! And they're working on 100% feature parity to ArcMap-- just &lt;em&gt;conveniently&lt;/em&gt; leaving one or two things out....&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the get go, I tried to use Pro, and given the fact that I did a ton of web gis patterns ArcGIS Server and the JS API, it was missing a critical feature, the ability to publish to ArcGIS Server. Okay cool, I waited, I asked devs and product managers every chance I got, "When will we get the ability to publish to ArcGIS Server direct? I can only publish to AGOL, and Portal, what gives?" The answer was always, "Let me get back to you..." Or (with a blank look) "You can publish to AGOL or Portal, that's so much better than silly server!"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let me tell, I was born, but I wasn't born yesterday.&lt;/strong&gt; The push for Portal, AGOL, and ArcGIS Pro as a replacement for ArcMap, isn't &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; about feature functionality. It's berthed quite the opposite situation, a little situation called your pocket book and predictable recurring revenue due to Esri. This product management decision to keep the ability to publish directly to server is a way to force users into the Salesforce, named user model. It's quite ingenious, if they were to try and upgrade ArcMap in place, but take these features away, customers would be rioting in the streets and it would probably violate some agreements. So, what to do? Spin up a new, flashy product that does SO MUCH MORE, and quietly take away the features that will not serve Esri's long-term business incentives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folks there will tell you, "Named Users! That's the way all software is going! Look at Microsoft, look at Salesforce!" Just one problem. You're not Salesforce, and you're certainly not Microsoft. And you shouldn't aspire to be the salesforce of GIS, why? Because your conflating two things that have diverging utility. Salesforce makes people money. There's not just ROI with Salesforce, it can freaking MAKE you money if you employ it right in your org. I'd happily pay for that. GIS, not so much. GIS doesn't help my cashflow, and it's delusional to think so. Whoever determined long ago to make this long-term decision to "Salesforce-ify" the ArcGIS Product needs to have their head checked. Named user models can be applied to where there is ubiquitous daily utility in your organization, for which Microsoft and Salesforce easily celebrate. Maps are great, but they aren't THAT great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will things get worse? Yes, I predict they will. You know those things called License Managers, build on 1980's technology that allow for concurrent usage? Yeah, they just "work" in a self-serve fashion? Yeah that self-serve situation will go away, and be replaced with the administrivia of spinning up a named user for someone, and then having to assign a "role" to them based on what function you think they are. Are you a level one? A level two? An analyst? A developer? Feel painted into a corner and typecast yet? You should, that's where things are going. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End to end, I can only imagine that once ArcMap goes away (just put two and two together here), ArcGIS Server goes away as well. Because it (ArcMap) was the only product that could feed it (Server). Thus, any WebGIS Patterns and Practices will REQUIRE the middleware of Portal and AGOL, and the named user burden that goes with it. If your business model relies on an ASP Commercial license of server, your wheels should really be spinning now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let's think like a crook here. How else could they hamper our freedoms to interoperability after this phase is "complete?". Oh, I've got one, how about we remove the RDBMS functionality (at least what's exposed to the end user), and move all multi-user editing workflows completely to the Portal/AGOL proprietary database? Goodbye SDE. Why not? They'll probably claim it's not Web-GIS friendly, etc., push Feature services in their stead. It'll take time, but I can assure you it'll probably happen when feature services get to that point of maturity. Because the incentive here is clear. &lt;strong&gt;End-to-end ingress AND egress to "The Platform" unlocked by the named user only.&lt;/strong&gt; If only they could find a way to license printed maps off of our plotters and charge anyone who happens to look at said maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only business partners and developers to survive this long-term war of attrition will have solutions that are completely DERIVATIVE and SUBSERVIENT of Esri's product. You job will be to sell the whole platform (don't all your customers want Collector?), and your little contribution will be analogous to a remora on a shark. You'll get by, ride the current of the beast, and be happy that you have a home, until Esri either determines that features from your cute product aren't in their product roadmap ( you live) OR they determine that they'd be "better" to offer this product, presumably because they're better suited to an end-customers are getting "confused" (you die). &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/03/giphy--1-.gif" alt=""&gt;
Either way, if you're a developer or business partner that has made money off of this stack. I suggest you start contingency planning right away. Don't aspire to be a remora. I don't see any course correction here in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2018/03/03/the-arcgis-identity-crisis-part-two/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">bec9fff8-83c6-4634-9445-3261553b144b</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 17:26:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Going serverless on my ghost blog with s3, route 53, and cloudfront</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt;
So I've had a blog for years, the first permutation was rockymountaingeo.com. I've always done hosting with some sort of LAMP server. This has been great. Super low cost, low maintinence linux setup. Blah blah blah. When I made the switch to projected.xyz, I decided on the ghost platform and used bitnami as my host, because hey had a nice setup with some premaid images and I could bring those to the aws cloud. The cost was on par with other hosts-- things start with a free tier and then move up to around 9 - 12 bucks per month, and I got my very own dedicated server. This has been great for the last few years. But something has been increasingly bothering me. Why the hell am I paying to "serve" something that I literally don't even maintain? If you can count on two hands the amount you blog in one year, you probably shouldn't be maintaining a server. With all this talk of reducing energy consumption and saving the earth, running a blog in a datacenter that's serving your crappy content from 5 years ago that seldom gets read doesn't really seem like earthly stewardship to me. After all that piece you wrote on alternative energy just might be served by a godaddy server that's getting its power from a coal fired power plant (ouch). These thoughts usually hit me around renewal season with my domains that I've purchased and have yet to use. Total guilt for good intentions gone to waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I made a decision. For one, I'm letting my domains that I'll never use lapse. Say goodbye to spatialjoin.com and spatialjoin.org.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hey &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/gistribe?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#gistribe&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ll be letting the domains &lt;a href="https://t.co/4O7hOi8Jyj"&gt;https://t.co/4O7hOi8Jyj&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://t.co/aoSYrhfULv"&gt;https://t.co/aoSYrhfULv&lt;/a&gt; expire in February, I don&amp;#39;t want to squat or receive $$$ on them because I &amp;quot;got to them first&amp;quot;. Hoping for good karma for my future domain pursuits by doing this. &lt;a href="https://t.co/c7zm8MGopR"&gt;pic.twitter.com/c7zm8MGopR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Mahrou ☁️ 📊 (@projectedxyz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/projectedxyz/status/957286608809598978?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;January 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of writing this, they're yours for the taking. More importantly, I decided that I'm done with the busienss of servers. Like really. Even Docker and Kubernetes (which sounds like some sort of obscure disease) are still to &lt;em&gt;server-like&lt;/em&gt; for me. Yeah, &lt;strong&gt;bold claim&lt;/strong&gt;, those are like bell bottoms-- you're gonna regret this in-between period in the future, trust me.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/DevDiscuss?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#DevDiscuss&lt;/a&gt; I haven&amp;#39;t used containers and feel like I will sit this out, let hype curves pass, and wait for more innovative devops.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Mahrou ☁️ 📊 (@projectedxyz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/projectedxyz/status/879877475282669568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patches, security, having a crappy DDOS target just sitting on the public internet (yeah done with that), serving up http only just seems kinda lame in 2018. This was compounded by the fact that amazon announced that they were raising their prime rates. That was it, the game was on, and I was going to get ahead of this however I could. I could no longer justify throwing away 10 bucks a month for crap. There had to be a better way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Amazon: &amp;quot;We raised the cost of prime!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Time to transition my blog to static pages and save 10 bucks a month!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The game of 🐈 and 🐁 continues&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Mahrou ☁️ 📊 (@projectedxyz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/projectedxyz/status/954731715775184896?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;January 20, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;And finally, to me the last straw was google's announcement that they were drawing a line in the sand on http come July of 2018.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Unofficially Say goodbye to http&lt;a href="https://t.co/v6tutX0FQR"&gt;https://t.co/v6tutX0FQR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Mahrou ☁️ 📊 (@projectedxyz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/projectedxyz/status/962347923446022144?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;February 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked around at various ways to go to a simplified architecture, increase performance, and save dough. &lt;strong&gt;Medium&lt;/strong&gt; seemed like a good deal (Free), but they stopped supporting custom domains. Also, medium is great but it's just an extension of the twitter. In essence an exit to the walled garden leads to a bigger walled garden. Also there's the vanity aspect of medium, they have claps, or applause (whatever it's called), it's just another way to keep score. Even from my first blog's inception, I never cared to put analytics or tracking on it, monetize, drive comments, optimize SEO, measure my social media reach, clout, or [insert popularity contest metric here]. My blog just needs to be something I can write about whenever I get inspired, and serve as as one-way vessel to send off my thoughts into the ether of the internet spirit world like one of those candle boats on a river in Japan. Toro nagashi-- &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T%C5%8Dr%C5%8D_nagashi"&gt;yeah I googled it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the technical challenge on the &lt;strong&gt;medium&lt;/strong&gt; avenue is, just... bush league (not worth a this meta-blog post about creating a blogging platform). No thanks. I kept looking. I learned about a &lt;a href="https://github.com/axitkhurana/buster"&gt;tool called &lt;strong&gt;buster&lt;/strong&gt; on github&lt;/a&gt;. It's a python module that is a static site generator for ghost... SWEET. Most folks use it for taking snapshots of their ghost blogs and creating static websites on github pages. That's great, but github pages doesn't offer ssl support on custom domains and with the google timeline on chrome support for http ending, I figured I needed to continue the search. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENTER AWS S3 w/Cloudfront CDN&lt;/strong&gt; That's when I found that you can actually host a static website on aws s3. There's tons of writeups on how to set this up, &lt;a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/WebsiteHosting.html"&gt;even this little handy one from Amazon&lt;/a&gt; Anyone that works with me or knows me well knows that I'm super bullish on Microsoft's Azure cloud-- I used it every chance I can get. But I'm no single cloud one-trick-pony. And if anyone REALLY knows me, they'd know that I started with AWS, and moved on to azure for more work, because that's where I've been able to create things working for fortune 500 firms that have EA agreements with Microsoft-- i.e. freebies. So for due diligence, I checked out the azure offer and feature for feature, I could have used azure, except for one thing... Amazon AWS offers free SSL certs in Cloudfront if you host your domain &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/certificate-manager/faqs/"&gt;dns records with them in aws route 53&lt;/a&gt; and use their global cdn... That sealed the deal folks. The cdn thing intruiged me too. This means that I could literally have edge servers around the world to host my blog content enterprise style and only pay for storage. So yes, even if you go &lt;strong&gt;serverless&lt;/strong&gt;, there is still always a server. I just upgraded my &lt;em&gt;server&lt;/em&gt; to what is likely biggest front of servers in the world-- coattails and commodities folks, ride em like the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style="border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:bold;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;Load Time&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:bold;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;Geography&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;268ms&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;Stockholm&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;383ms&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;Melbourne&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;185ms&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;San Jose&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;289ms&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;New York&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td style="font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;vertical-align:top"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;Yeah look below. This is austrailia in under a second, &lt;strong&gt;because I can&lt;/strong&gt;. LOL &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/02/austrailia.PNG" alt="Austrailia in under a second, because I can"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did I have to do? This is by no means a technical step by step but rather a punch list high level stuff I needed to get done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moved my domain DNS (first) and domain wholly over to AWS Route 53 (one time fee of $12 bucks; well worth it)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created s3 static website using amazon's step-by-step referenced above  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created a cloudfront distribution that points to my s3 bucket address &lt;a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/website-hosting-cloudfront-walkthrough.html"&gt;with this walkthrough&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assigned a free ssl certificate using AWS Certificate Manager &lt;a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonCloudFront/latest/DeveloperGuide/using-https.html"&gt;with this walkthrough&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Putty'd in to my bitnami server running ghost and ran pip install buster to get buster  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generated the static website with buster &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2018/02/buster.gif" alt=""&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh how handy, with the bitnami server build, the aws CLI tools were already installed. So I &lt;a href="https://stormpath.com/blog/ultimate-guide-deploying-static-site-aws"&gt;followed the instuctions here&lt;/a&gt; to push my website directly to s3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still to do&lt;/strong&gt; I need to fix my rss and home links. I'd also plan to automate this all in one script that'll run buster, fix the home/rss links/feeds, then push to aws. That's a low bar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;, I've reduced my monthly hosting bill by 99%, increased security, rid myself of server/patch management, and increased my little blog's resiliency to that of an internet fortress with the giant mote of aws. I'd also like to think that I'm eliminating waste somehow, but I have yet to see a quantitative metric to prove as such-- other than my bank account. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My old binami server is now just a dev server that I shut down when I'm not using, so that &lt;em&gt;presumably&lt;/em&gt; some bitcoin bro in his parents basement can repurpose those cores to achieve his lamborghini/bugatti dreams.  &amp;lt;- But that's a blog post for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;🍺&lt;strong&gt;Cheers&lt;/strong&gt;🍺,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2018/02/17/going-serverless-on-my-ghost-blog-with-s3-and-cloudfront/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">cccb6349-3cb5-4a1d-b864-3cd93f930b42</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 05:20:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The tool shouldn't matter</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Why is it that thought leaders in this field care so much about the tools that you use to solve problems with GIS? The argument for the use of Esri versus non Esri software seems to never get old on social media. There's an unspoken undercurrent frustration with commercial GIS Software. The title of this blog is "the tool doesn't matter". That means that the road that gets you to the solution shouldn't matter as much as the problem you're trying to solve and the solution that you came up with. Over the past two weekends I've been installing wood floors in my house. Depending on who I talked to, I would need "just a table saw". Another trusted person told me that I could get everything done with a chop saw and a jig saw. To undercut my door jams, I could use a trim saw, a double sided pull saw or an oscillating multitool with an undercut attachment. These "right tools" would vary depending on who I talked to and what they thought was right for them. But my real friends would preface, &lt;strong&gt;"you'll find what's right for you"&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I installed the floors my own way... I used a sliding miter saw to chop, a circular saw to rip boards, and an oscillating multitool to undercut. When I was done with the floors and showed the product to my friends, they did ask questions as to which tools I used to get the job done, but there was no judgement. In the end, they ultimately judged the result. Use what's right for you and you're ultimately judged on your craftsmanship, not on the brand of tool you used. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a converse, analagous fashion, why are so many people in Geo so fixated on whether you're using ArcGIS, or qGIS or R or Python? Alternatives are great to the norm (like Nirvana in the 90's), but does that mean that you're only cool if you embrace the alternative? There's no need to become a judgemental zealot to get everyone to believe what you think. Rather, why don't you spend more time creating products, rather than judging how someone else might have created theirs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, I'm extremely bullish on Open Source and commercial alternatives-- they will provide more substance to one's experience and resume. They will also make you more flexible with your approach. Conversely, so will peppering your stack with some trusted commercial solutions if you claim to be an Open Source shop. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2017/05/Too-Many-Tools1.jpg" alt="too many tools"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The times are changing, Boundless Geo was just awarded a huge contract for the NGA-- ya know, that agency that has been known in headlines as the &lt;a href="https://theantimedia.org/agency-dangerous-nsa/"&gt;Agency that's more powerful than the CIA that you've never heard of.&lt;/a&gt;. So tides are certainly shifting, organically. They can't be forced. So there's no reason to judge. Instead, sit back and enjoy the options we have to get the job done. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;product&lt;/strong&gt; of the tooling should be the main thing that matters. This isn't an argument on coding versus button pushing. Given that mostly all data and technology, (spatial is included here) has been democratized and commoditized, I think most traditionally schooled GIS folks should learn to code for web development (JavaScript) and or general purpose (python), and if you code using api's maintained by a (heaven forbid) proprietary for profit enterprise, you shouldn't be ashamed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's why I like &lt;a href="https://thespatialcommunity.com/"&gt;The Spatial Community on Slack&lt;/a&gt;, they've got channels for whatever suits your fancy spatially.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2017/05/06/the-tool-shouldnt-matter/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a0eab1e4-3c5e-4d06-b6ea-f0132918207f</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 20:06:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A disposition for Innovation</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This is certainly not a technical article, but as a technologist, this article rings true to my experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's the best disposition that sets you up to innovate? Don't give a shit. Read on for an explanation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd like to think I've done some innovative things. But when I hear the word innovator or innovation, a bunch of images swirl in my head-- most are quite negative and cliché for our day and age: A young up-and-comer who thinks they need to embody the worst traits of our best innovators in order to come across as successful. Not caring about cost, and trying too hard (all moonshots) to fail at endeavors (because that's what you're supposed to do right?). How about this one: resampling something great, barely tweaking what was done, slapping your name on it, and calling it innovation. Even better, carrying yourself around to take credit for that one thing you did way back when, and taking credit for the whole thing as a visionary-- when in fact it was a team effort, and you never gave credit to the team?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't call yourself a visionary, a leader, a luminary, a pioneer, a trailblazer, an evangelist, or at the very worst, an innovator. You might actually embody some of these characteristics, but it doesn't make your identity. Once you begin to take stock of all the things you've done, and begin to weave a story of success, forgetting about your wasted investments, whilst rounding off the corners of the struggle, or forgetting the teamwork that made this great thing happen, you become highly fragile-- constantly looking backwards and validating what happened, and telling yourself the stories that you'd like to hear over and over in your head, and lashing out at anything that might refute that story of success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's the beginning of the fall. It sucks, and it is the reason that most true innovation doesn't get followed up with further home runs. It's not that you get too comfy, it's that you believe that you've arrived, and if you're on a team where this dynamic becomes borne within just one team member, things can get toxic quickly. Labels and job titles that describe who you'd like people to think you are serve to strengthen the aforementioned complex. [Insert Signature, send email, and kick back in your chair with machinations of what the receiver might think of you.] I've got news: There are two camps of receiver to your self-proclamations of greatness. Some will seek to flatter you and validate this image of yourself (time and time again), and some just frankly won't give a shit. Both camps of people are important to the cycle of innovation for good reason. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first camp (the flatterers) are really fun to party with. You'll find them at conferences, carrying around their titles, labels, and fancy +1 colorful conference badges. They know lots and lots of people, but their relationships are often shallow. Happenings of the industry are cliff-noted and retold, as if they were in on it. Everyone's their friend, nothing bad ever happens. In the marketplace, these folks will most successfully rise to the ranks of sales-- which is absolutely necessary. Some might occasionally be misplaced into a management role, where they spend much time overtaking and one upping their subordinates. Some might be placed in a technologist role, where they will fake it and make excuses until they're fired or get bored and move onto another unsuspecting firm or organization. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second camp, the folks that don't give a shit. These folks aren't ignoring your greatness, they just either want you to prove yourself (so won't offer flattery), or (rare) they might see your label or title as a threat. This is the camp of the folks who work in teams to get things done. They don't need constant praise, because they get value from the work, not the retelling of the work. This camp is more likely to embody the real innovators. The story of the great work usually gets retold, just usually by the folks in camp one. Let them, it's their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've honestly slid between both camps here. They both absolutely need to exist. But I've found myself lately just getting value and happiness from the pursuit of knowledge rather than power. I'm more in the second camp. Both camps, let's call them the tellers and the doers, are inextricably linked with one another in the cycle of innovation. But if you truly want to innovate, you must focus on the doing, with the humility of someone who doesn't give a shit about anything, except for the obstacle in the path. Let's decode the statement "humility of someone who doesn't give a shit". When taken out of context, this makes no sense. Here's what I mean by this statement: we're not talking about wonton disregard for all shits, we mean someone who sees little value in the shits that happened in the past (good or bad) as props to hoist oneself up on, corporate mythology to cloud the task at hand, or past things to sweep under the rug as failures. What is left is honest humility, and an eagerness to just make things happen-- and give no shits otherwise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"For there is nothing either good or bad, but thinking makes it so." - Shakespeare&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So start where you are now, and don't spend time worrying about proving your greatness to others, just go out and do the thing you're supposed to do. Do it well. Because in the end, the value is in the doing. Celebrations rarely last longer than a day, or even an hour. Let the others tell, they are there for a reason. At first glance most think it's to take credit for what you're doing-- while that might be a motive sometimes, please don't give a shit. The silver lining is that they afford you the time to keep learning and innovating. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;“Never retract. Never explain. Get it done and let them howl.” Benjamin Jowett&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ryan Holiday (@RyanHoliday) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RyanHoliday/status/768878867427815424"&gt;August 25, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2016/09/24/a-disposition-for-innovation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">c95963e9-8fac-498e-a70d-163a62883f4a</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 22:49:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The ArcGIS Identity Crisis</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been working with the ArcGIS Suite of products since I was first indoctrinated into the cult of Commercial GIS Software during my Geography undergrad at the University of Texas at San Antonio. It was so simple then to me to use desktop GIS to deliver maps. In the first decade of this century, Esri has been growing its product suite by leaps and bounds, and in my opinion, with constant growing pains along the way. In full disclosure, the ArcGIS product suite makes up a large part of my stack right now. And I see huge value in what it brings to every day challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following highlights a specific concern of mine. And that's (in the title) the ArcGIS Identity model. To further define this terminology, identity can be used interchangeably with the named user. &lt;a href="https://www.esri.com/products/arcgis-capabilities/identity"&gt;Here's a link to the definition from Esri.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon reading the above link, you can gather that the mantra of ArcGIS Everywhere is alive: you can use the identity everywhere-- COTS Apps, custom apps, through Esri's business partners, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sowhatsthebeef"&gt;So what's the beef?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consultant, who creates temporary GIS projects to augment AEC projects, I have to share my data with my clients and stakeholders on the web or via mobile apps. Unfortunately, according to Esri, if I publish content to ArcGIS.com, I can only share this data internal to my organization. Esri goes further to insist that my organization only consists of my employees and contractors. Anyone beyond that must have their own ArcGIS.com account. Spinning up a temporary account for a client to view data on a project that I've undertaken for them is a no no. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I to do? Well, there are some new kids on the block with less restrictive licensing models. But I'm so entrenched now with AGOL, is it too late to switch horses? I think not. Right now my main usage of AGOL are web apps, and Collector for ArcGIS. All I need is a smart web map strategy, and a mobile strategy and I have the potential to ditch the shackles of the restrictive identity constraints. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Esri (just to double check), Mapbox, Fulcrum and Carto (previously CartoDB) for their take on allowing me to spin up accounts for my clients for the duration of a project. Below are snippets from each.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="arcgischat"&gt;ArcGIS Chat&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/AGOL.PNG" alt="ArcGIS Chat"&gt;
I even stated, "Since your pricing model is based on users". Maybe to jar some reason into this front-line chat dude, that maybe their stance is actually hurting their ability to get more users?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fulcrumchat"&gt;Fulcrum Chat&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/fulcrum1.PNG" alt="Fulcrum Chat"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/fulcrum2.PNG" alt="Fulcrum Chat2"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="mapbox"&gt;Mapbox&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Mapbox1-1.PNG" alt="Mapbox1"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/mapbox2.PNG" alt="Mapbox2"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Mapbox3.PNG" alt="Mapbox3"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Mapbox4.PNG" alt="Mapbox4"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Mapbox5.PNG" alt="Mapbox5"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="carto"&gt;Carto&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Carto0.PNG" alt="Carto"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://projected.xyz/content/images/2016/08/Carto1.PNG" alt="Carto1"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="synopsis"&gt;Synopsis&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a misspelling that propagated across all chats and emails. I said "I there instead of "Hi there". Besides that, the meat of this is that Esri needs to get with the program if they want broader usage of their toolset. AGOL is great functionality wise, but if I have to put my clients through a toll booth to show them data, it’s a non-starter. Especially when I can go down the street to MapBox, Carto, or Fulcrum for my Web Mapping and Mobile GIS Needs, and their licensing model isn't a consultant's nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is extreme hubris in this one component/approach of the ArcGIS product, and I can foresee that if things don't change, more will consider some of these alternatives. Did you see the Carto (CartoDB at the time) Boat that parked right up at the Marina during the Esri UC in 2015? It was touted as the "UnConference Boat".  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Day 2 of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EsriUC?src=hash"&gt;#EsriUC&lt;/a&gt;, day 2 of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CartoDB"&gt;@cartoDB&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/UCboat?src=hash"&gt;#UCboat&lt;/a&gt; starts soon around 11! &lt;a href="https://t.co/kDgUgkxXis"&gt;pic.twitter.com/kDgUgkxXis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Thompson (@andrewbt) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/andrewbt/status/623540313466892288"&gt;July 21, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that huge Mapbox Party that was thrown at the Esri UC this year on the USS Midway?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;At USS Midway, an aircraft carrier. Thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Mapbox"&gt;@Mapbox&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EsriUC2016?src=hash"&gt;#EsriUC2016&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gruntify"&gt;@gruntify&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gispeople"&gt;@gispeople&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/IIfJuE6wwj"&gt;pic.twitter.com/IIfJuE6wwj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igor Stjepanovic (@igor_au) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/igor_au/status/747986656746053632"&gt;June 29, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies are not some fly by night hipsters that aren't going anywhere. This is no longer just Open Source Alternatives vs Esri. These commercial entities are backed by communities/ seeking a less restrictive alternative, Venture Capital that sees an underserved market, and developers who strive to create a product that not only stands up to the legacy offering, but raises it to a new standard of interoperability and flexibility. Make no mistake, they are out to eat Esri's lunch. As a user that's been mated to the ArcGIS Platform for years, I'm happy that there's some healthy competition in the web and mobile space, and I look forward to giving it a whirl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2016/08/06/the-arcgis-identity-crisis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">d932cb7e-3e2c-4fa8-ab0e-a1ad0dfb8f6d</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 04:10:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GeoEgo out of control</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm finishing up a book from Ryan Holiday, called "Ego is the Enemy". It's for all intents and purposes a follow on to his previous book "The Obstacle is the Way". To be completely honest, these books (If I was a computer) form my "operating system" for how I've approached my life lately. Ego is the Enemy really spelled out to me what's important in life and more specifically-- what really matters in what you do with your life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's allowed me not to take myself so seriously, and also, not to place such a value on silly things, like job titles, whether or not people "know of" me, how many followers on twitter I have, whether or not I score a meeting with an executive at my firm that would remember me, who's checked out my LinkedIn, or care about if someone mentioned work I've done. All that I just mentioned are distractions from my true work, which is just working with data for internal and external projects as a consultant. Many of those ego feeding pursuits will tend to bleed out of the workday and into personal time too, with constant app refreshes, and keeping score on social media. I'm not advocating to unplug from everything besides work, school, and family in my life, but rather elevate those activities to the top of the heap, and stop focusing on those activities that just drain my energy and time (the scarcest resource). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's the punchline? What does that have to do with Ego? Well, I just discovered slack, and there's a great gis community up there called The Spatial Community. I was driven there because I saw a tweet about a premium slack community that was being proposed on Kickstarter called MapClub. What irked me was that you would get access to three mapping "Luminaries" by joining for the low low cost of $99 per person, and that the first ten backers would be considered founding members. At first, one side of my brain said "do it man! You have no idea what slack is, but this will give you access to a luminary (yeah, a luminary), and if you get in now, you'll be a founding member!". Then the other side of my brain kicked in, and asked questions like, "Why fragment an already established community instead of making it better if you don't agree with some things? This dude isn't a Jack Dangermond, Roger Tomlinson, or Charles Picquet, but he's proclaiming himself and a few others as a luminary. Now let's back up and try to decode that word: Luminary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-mcGyTWJKRSA/V5bdGZdYwPI/AAAAAAAAI3A/kEO37E3qP3IsV33ecbff694jP0IQscCCQCLcB/h119/Luminary.PNG" alt="alt text"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This struck me: "A person who inspires or influences others, especially one prominent in a particular sphere." So why would you need to start something new, when there's an existing community with over 1200 users in it? Can't you use your influence there? No, instead it was insinuated that the reason it was $99 a head was to "keep the crazies out". Hmm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What also has irked me is the premium price tag, that's way above and beyond the Slack Pricing plus model at $12.50 a head. Where's the rest go? To the bouncers at the door that keep the crazies out? This is starting to look like a "who loves me? And how much will they pay to access me contest" Or as I thought in my head, Tidal4Geo. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that aside, I decided to look into Slack's TOS, to see if this was even allowed. Section 6.7 states that you can’t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://slack.com/terms-of-service"&gt;: sublicense, resell, rent, lease, transfer or assign (except as permitted in Section 16) the Service or its use, or offer the Service on a time share basis to any third party&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I decided to look into Kickstarter's TOS, and prohibited items to see if this was allowed. [ Here's where things get interesting] (&lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/rules/prohibited"&gt;https://www.kickstarter.com/rules/prohibited&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-dimqLC7Scx4/V5bmJXwZPsI/AAAAAAAAI3Y/-x2LuSbg_KQnWjl14ROhFVHXKHIXi5zLQCCo/s802/Resale.PNG" alt="alt text"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what's the reward? Let's pull that from the site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-S_QEtaMscHQ/V5bn3F4ncGI/AAAAAAAAI30/FdLviLvna3weK6GO9ncWh730D4jZjtSeACCo/s686/Membership.PNG" alt="alt text"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking with me thus far... We're almost there. The benefits of joining, or rather the reward (Kickstarter Terms Verbiage) is membership to a slack group. Doesn't slack's TOS state that you can't resell, rent, lease, transfer or assign the Service? Think about the fact that you're purchasing a membership for a Slack group through what's presented as an affiliate broker (of which it's not), Kickstarter to handle the transaction. Isn't this web phishing 101? I know my company made me take some sort of training like this. The premise is, if you see a different url in the address bar that's different from the product or brand you're about to purchase, it's most likely the first "red flag". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-BRrNEiAtBxw/V5bsU83j4pI/AAAAAAAAI4E/YmrT5Y0yfnMhIQxWu_J5WEIfVbJne721QCCo/s888/redflag.jpg" alt="alt text"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack has its own Terms of Service, and by joining via slack (not through resale), you're subject to those should they decide to change those terms of service in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-z5yepLejQX8/V5btud-44qI/AAAAAAAAI4Y/reAuJLMVuK4YPvolRsRQpY3TNcTEbRASQCCo/s746/slack.PNG" alt="alt text"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That above means you're paying $99 dollars per year to an entity other than the service provider (Slack), for access to an exclusive service from said service provider (a private slack group), and Slack can shut off the lights at any time. Who do you go to then with your grievance? Slack? Kickstarter? The Luminaries? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for anyone who's tempted to join, go for it. But there should be questions like, who's handling the membership annual transactions after one year? How long will kickstarter handle this as the storefront for the resale of the private slack group?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really don't care if the MapClub treehouse survives or dies, because I don't pay for friends.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole campaign speaks to a larger issue in GIS. It's the feeling that GIS (and it's self-proclaimed superstars) are somehow unique or special just by virtue of being. We don't need walled garden clubhouses with exclusive access to its "movers and shakers". Because the bottom line is that while you're out there spinning up self-congratulatory clubs as proof of your popularity, some group of real movers and shakers are coding up the next Big Thing that will use geospatial tech (think Pokémon Go). Do you even think these shops refer to themselves as Mapping luminaries? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2016/07/26/geoego-point-of-no-return/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f61504ff-442b-4866-a16f-385a65df2d70</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 05:38:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My Statement of Purpose to Grad School</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Dear University of Colorado Denver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am applying for your Masters of Engineering in Geomatics and GIS. I have a Bachelors in Geography, gained in 2006, from the University of Texas at San Antonio. I have been working since then here in Colorado in the geospatial sector ever since. I am currently employed at a local engineering firm CH2M as a GIS Analyst in the Oil, Gas, and Chemicals group. In a 10% role I am also the geospatial technical steward for the firm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been searching for a program like this for a very long time. American academia is littered with GIS certificate programs, and master’s degrees, with very little time spent on the fundamentals of geomatics and geospatial technology. In the United States, there exists an ever-widening gap between what we call, “survey”, and GIS—whereby the former is looked upon as a trade, and the latter is viewed as a niche career with heavy dependence on vendor specific software suites. Because this happens to be a phenomena heavily present in the United States, the long-term effects of perpetuating this will ultimately result in low geospatial literacy in the United States when compared internationally. More participation in programs like yours will serve to mend this issue, and I seek to be part of that solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further expound upon this gap in knowledge between these roles, there is also a heavy dependence on easy solutions by utilizing GUI-driven GIS software. Whilst there is nothing inherently wrong with the spirit of this convenience, I am interested in learning the science behind the tools, and arming myself with the ability to perform the same analysis in long-hand, should this be required of me in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has also been a rebirth of the photogrammetric practice with the prevalence of data collected with Unmanned Aerial Vehicles. Given this flood of high resolution data, there needs to be more consciousness of the requisite science that must be practiced to deliver quality, accurate outputs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In closing, I knew that at one point it would be time to resume my education beyond my Bachelors. I always told myself that I wouldn’t attain my masters until I found a world issue or opportunity that I needed to pour my passion into. I truly believe that time is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely, &lt;br&gt;
Alex Mahrou&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2015/08/01/my-statement-of-purpose-to-grad-school/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">0ec6ded4-6269-459b-9124-86ba2b651fac</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 20:49:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>5 Takeaways from the 2015 Esri User Conference</title><description>&lt;p&gt;After letting the Esri UC Plenary sink in for some time, I thought I'd take some time to right down some takeways. Things are rapidly changing, and the ArcGIS platform is expanding, in some good ways, and in some other ways that will serve to widen the gap between developers and users. I'll preface this-- I'm a huge proponent of Esri's technology, and one really has to dig to find anything that negative with it. The good far outweighs the bad with their offerings. There's no other software organization (to my knowledge) that makes Philanthropy, R&amp;amp;D, and Education their loss leaders to the extent to they do, except for maybe Google. Let's begin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="1esrifinallyhasacompetitortogoogleearthitmightbegoogleearth"&gt;1. Esri finally has a competitor to Google Earth-- it might be Google Earth?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's Google Earth-- on steroids. I haven’t done further digging, but could ArcGIS Earth be the lovechild born out of whatever backroom deal was hatched out of Google and Esri last year when Google decided to exit enterprise maps? That's when Esri announced a plan for Google's customers to come on over to the ArcGIS platform as an alternative. I thought this was funny at first, but it seems as though it certainly had merit, and now one might assume that ArcGIS Earth has its roots in the secret sauce that was Google Earth Pro. I'm interested to see if they killed off any import and export functionality (but keeping KML) in favor of locking folks in to ArcGIS.com-- purely speculative, but we'll see. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="2thingsaregettingreallyeasy"&gt;2. Things are getting really easy...&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The products are improving immensely but there are some fundamental shifts in the learning curve for a GIS user that's utilizing their software. Now you can actually deploy your own app to a myriad of different devices with just a few button clicks. Also with web appbuilder you can literally spin up a javascript web app in minutes as well. No need to write a single line of code. Achieving this is actually quite a feat from the perspective of development. But to literally dumb things down to this level will hurt a folks on a few fronts...  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="esrisbusinesspartnerswhocreateappsmightbeturnedintocompetitors"&gt;*    Esri's Business Partners who create apps might be turned into competitors.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would I need to hire a Developer to create a great app if I could easily just do it through Esri? We have to think about the ever growing footprint of activities that Esri is now participating in. With convenience comes dependence on this platform. It's brilliant, but is it doing too much?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="esrisuserbaseisnotgettingchallenged"&gt;* Esri's user base is not getting challenged.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these developments are great, but honestly could be making us all soft and limiting career potential. Spinning up a quick app is great for a government, or an emergency response. But I don't think that this should be in the Academic offering in our schools-- for which ArcGIS is now free for K - 12. Showing kids the power of place is good, but the unspoken incentive for Esri is to get these kiddo's drinking the koolaid at a very young age, and when they grow up, they can easily just be good obedient users in this environment. For the folks that I work with every day, we have an index that we keep called FIO. That stands for figure it out. If we teach kids, and users that all they'll ever need to do is "configure" and not solve a problem by taking a deep dive and learning something the hard way, they'll never really feel the reward of having done something challenging on their own. They'll take what they've built up on to the next school or career and say, "oh yeah I can create a web app, or even a smartphone application on any device, all that you have to do is buy this software and I'll configure it for you."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's no room for the user to develop their own secret sauce, but rather all of the secret sauce is now part of the platform. The end users will benefit, but the person that deployed it has a huge dependence on an outside party. This will not spark curiosity within the lower ranks of organizations or more alarmingly within K-12 Schools or colleges. This will ultimately result in a low FIO and technical literacy across the board. So ultimately there is still a great career path for Esri Developers, just work for Esri or a non-commercial entity that won't compete on any level with Esri. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just finished the biography of Elon Musk (Elon Musk: Tesla, SpaceX, and the Quest for a Fantastic Future), and in the book there was a story about how Elon was attempting to get SpaceX off the ground in the early days by trying to purchase a rocket from Russia. This was becoming frustrating, as the Russians were hard to deal with, and it also would make SpaceX extremely depended on an outside entity, something that Lockeed Martin and Northrup Grumman do all of the time. Because the legacy launch business companies where so dependent upon outside entities, and add that Russia wasn't taking SpaceX seriously in their conversations, Musk took it upon himself to begin the process of building something from scratch. Two things happened thereafter that are now instrumental in the success of this company: 1. SpaceX rockets are fully Made in the USA, 2. SpaceX can launch a rocket at a considerable cost savings because they didn't follow the herd when it came to legacy supply chains. What does this have to do with the decline of the GIS user? If people don't seek to build things themselves, they will miss out on future opportunities to do something extraordinary and everything they create with Esri will always have a considerable overhead to go along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="3esrisdesktopgisisgettingfragmented"&gt;3. Esri's Desktop GIS is getting fragmented&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are TONS of Esri products and more coming online all of the time. But the only issue that I'd like to Address here is the fragmentation that will continue to get worse between their desktop analysis software: ArcGIS Desktop, and ArcGIS Pro. &lt;br&gt;
First off, the only technology crash in the plenary happened with ArcGIS Pro, when two Molokai high school students were presenting how they used GIS for their analysis.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;wish I could be as calm &amp;amp; collected with a technology blip presenting to 16k+ people as the Molokai students &lt;a href="https://t.co/Zf8YwruSJ7"&gt;pic.twitter.com/Zf8YwruSJ7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EsriUC?src=hash"&gt;#EsriUC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Turner (@ajturner) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ajturner/status/623255772395368448"&gt;July 20, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;They clicked a single button, then it froze on them. I thought to myself, "Finally this has been my experience with this software from the get-go". Given this, these girls recovered gracefully. But what begged more of an explanation was when the girls admitted that they had only learned ArcGIS Pro 48 hours ago, and that they ultimately did all of their analysis in ArcGIS Desktop. That was really uncool to put these girls through that, but it's been an analogous approach to how this product has been heaped on to the whole user base from the get go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We've been presented with a product that for the most part is a complete redundancy to the legacy product. Not only that, it's cumbersome-- you click on a menu and it should just pop up. That's the experience that we're all used to in ArcGIS Desktop. If this product is to be an improvement, it just can't be as good as the legacy experience, it needs to beat it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding fragmentation, apparently most of their new tools and development will get done for ArcGIS Pro, and ArcGIS Desktop will not receive the same functions in all cases of new features. This is going to get extremely confusing and has the potential to really frustrate people if they have to open up multiple programs to get their jobs done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="4esriisnowinthebusinessofdrones"&gt;4. Esri is now in the business of drones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a video from the Plenary of their software. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://video.esri.com/watch/4652/unmanned-aerial-systems"&gt;https://video.esri.com/watch/4652/unmanned-aerial-systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like how they framed everything by how long the entire process took. In my quest to develop a successful workflow, I've seen many vendors fall on their face after a successful flight and then it comes time to process the data into something you can use. From the video, this looks promising. Hopefully they'll get a leg up on Autodesk’s Recap and Memento products by inclusion of Ground Control Points, IMU Data, and Camera calibration to truly get about a photogrammetric solution. Only time will tell...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="5martinomalleyisawesome"&gt;5. Martin O'Malley is awesome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esri invited presidential candidate Martin O'Malley for the keynote speech. He's an amazing orator, but what's so cool is that he understands the power of maps when it comes to making decisions. He was able to back up how he made decisions as Mayor and Governor with data. My tagline that I learned from Data Science pursuits is "If it can be measured, it can be improved". This seems to be his approach to solving real-world problems like crime, poverty, and climate change. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://video.esri.com/watch/4666"&gt;https://video.esri.com/watch/4666&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2015/07/30/5-takeaways-from-the-esri-user-conference-plenary/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a4491ee5-ba4a-44f4-ba0b-d0c671599c6b</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 18:34:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Enterprise Mobile GIS Software Functionality</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The following is a best features/drawbacks from my experience in trying to find a suitable mobile platform for the Enterprise.Things have come a long way in the mobile enterpriseI define Enterprise Mobile GIS software as a robust field software with the added benefit of synchronizing over a network connection. Other software that you need to dock via usb and synchronize can be great and robust too, but given the times we live in this should be the core feature of any Enterprise Mobile GIS Solution.I'm only taking a small sample from Esri, Trimble, and Fulcrum. There are more out there, and I'd like to hear about them.EsriEsri gets the largest write up, not only because they have the most software, but also because this is where I play the most. If the tone is critical, it's because I'm passionate about its success. The ArcGIS Platform in regards to mobile is broad. But given the number of offerings, it is bordering on becoming completely fragmented and lacking a clear message across all available Operating Systems. Right now you can choose from ArcPad, ArcGIS for Windows Mobile on Windows Mobile, ArcGIS for Windows Mobile on Windows OS, ArcGIS for Android, ArcGIS for iOS, ArcGIS for Windows Phone, and Collector for Android, Collector for iOS. Making software across multiple platforms does not make a solution fragmented. What makes a solution fragmented is attempting to address multiple platforms and not having a focused, homogeneous functionality matrix across it. ArcGIS for Windows Mobile &amp;amp; ArcPadBest FeaturesThe biggest differentiator for my current Enterprise (and most would  probably argue) is disconnected editing. This feature is only found in ArcGIS for Windows Mobile or ArcPad, which only works on Windows OS, and Windows Mobile. If you want disconnected editing out of the box in this ecosystem, you can't find it in any other fashion within this offering. DrawbacksNo one buys this hardware any more. Everyone wants an iPad or to use their smartphone. The tablets for this are either not able to be ruggedized, lacking a true NMEA GPS beyond windows location api, or are way to expensive if they check all of the boxes. ArcPad is a relic that less and less people want to use. It works great for editing in the field, but its connection to 10.2 web adapters is tricky, and not something I'm comfortable deploying. ArcGIS for iOS, Android, and Windows PhoneBest featuresThe UI is consistent and the functionality is consistent across the offering. It's easy to use. It really just works. You can configure your web adapter in ArcGIS for Server to act as your mobile content server. All you need is some json code and you are up and running with whatever security scheme you have implemented in your enterprise. #awesomeDrawbacksNo disconnected editing. So you are really limited to the geographies where you have a constant connection. It makes for a really great demo when you're connected. But makes no sense off the grid, where the majority of collection really happens. Unfortunately, they haven't had any plans of expanding this app to accept disconnected editing. Which makes it an incomplete offering. The lack of documentation for utilizing your own ArcGIS Mobile Content server is buried within one pdf that you can link to through an FAQ on the mobile site at resources.arcgis.com. MAPS.pdf.Collector on Android &amp;amp; iOSBest feature(s)The promise of disconnected editing. DrawbacksWhy release a product who's first release only had the capability to collect point geometry, when you had a 75% complete software in the native ArcGIS App for Smartphones and Tablets? At the UC last year, the Product Managers signaled that Collector (available on iOS, Android) would provide disconnected editing in the next release. They have since backpedaled and we'll have to wait until next January for 10.2.1-- which will be the better part of a year since they announced it at the UC last year. &lt;a href="https://blogs.esri.com/esri/arcgis/2013/10/10/collector-v10-2-is-coming-soon/Collector"&gt;https://blogs.esri.com/esri/arcgis/2013/10/10/collector-v10-2-is-coming-soon/Collector&lt;/a&gt; also necessitates ArcGIS online, ArcGIS for Organizations, or Portal for ArcGIS account. So be prepared to pay a premium if you don't want your data to be exposed in a public cloud. The concern with this release is why would you start a brand new piece of software when the Native ArcGIS for iOS, Android, and Windows Phone was only missing the disconnected editing feature? With this release the alarming trend is that mobile software from this vendor is getting to 75%, then it's off to the next shiny object. Trimble TeraFlexBest FeaturesTheir Enterprise Solution called TeraFlex is simply awesome and has great potential. This is far from a fragmented strategy. The UI and functionality matrix is actually homogeneous regardless if you are on Android, iOS, or even Windows Mobile (other vendors should take note). The price-point is cheap as well. It offers disconnected editing to boot. Let's not forget it's offered by Trimble, so there's sure to be some future incentive to weave this into their hardware scheme-- for which you can count on quality.DrawbacksFor me this is almost enterprise right now. It necessitates the use of the Trimble cloud to act as the middle man between you and the data. Real-time integration into their cloud would be tough to maneuver and might not be the mission of this software solution right now. Because of the low price point, it's natural that Trimble's first aim is to capture the low-end market. I'm praying that bringing a 100% self-hosted enterprise solution is on the horizon, with the support for your own tiles to boot. And if that's the case, I'm all in.FulcrumBest FeaturesRobust online form creation. Low cost. Integration of your own tiles. A REST API that allows you to hook into their cloud with your own data sources to accommodate a real-time workflow. You get the same experience across multiple platforms with this software as well.DrawbacksNo support for lines or polygons. They even went as far as to make a blog post defending this stance. Telling customers why they don't need a feature in software in this fashion might be considered condescending. Utilities, oil and gas, and environmental customers all need to collect these geometries in the field. On a positive note, I have heard that they are testing this, and it will be offered in the future when they get it right.------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------In conclusionThis is not an attempt to rank software, these are just my summations (personal opinions) thus far. I'm sure there is other software out there, and I'd love to learn about it. I blog so that I can share what I got right, and learn from the things I got wrong or missed.Trimble and Fulcrum have a laser focus on the critical elements across platforms from a product management standpoint. That is a disruptive thing to other vendors that might have too many offerings, lack consistency in critical elements, and spend too much time offering new semi-functional redundancies in software every year; when they should spend time completing the software that works, and sun-setting the software that does not.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2013/10/21/enterprise_mobile_gis_software_functionality/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">c11e1122-406b-40d0-99ce-cde441c9dc06</guid><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 03:02:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Trimble Juno 3D Review</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So I got my hands on the new Juno 3D a few weeks ago. Now I'm thinking to myself, how the am I supposed to review this thing? When I get my hands on the latest and greatest Trimble device, I will set up a gauntlet of accuracy tests-- but this is a Juno. You don't get a Juno for accuracy. You see the paradigm is shifting... In a world where geographic data needs to be both timely and accurate,  more folks are realizing that the timely aspect is becoming much more important. What good is super spatially accurate data if it can't get to the decision makers in a timely fashion? When I was in the Gulf of Mexico during the Oil Spill, and subsequent emergency responses since, the main goal was to get dots on the map as soon as possible. It's not just to appease the public or some folks in D.C., instead it's about showing folks that you are actively working to assess the situation-- it's proof that you are doing your job. The new Juno is the way to go for GIS Data Collection in Emergency Responses and other scenarios which require the real-time picture of any given situation. HardwareThe new Juno comes in two models, one with phone functionality, and one without-- the 3D and 3B respectively. There are a few more frills on the 3D besides the modem hardly worth mentioning, like Microsoft Office Mobile.The thing is much more durable than previous models. In fact, I believe that the previous years models didn't even include an IP rating. The new Juno 3D and 3B are IP54 rated, which is quite an improvement, given that the price point of this device has not changed.When you hold it in your hand, you know it's much more durable than its predecessors, but it's still small enough to fit in your pocket. The 5mp camera is much improved as well (up from 3mp from its predecessor).One interesting tidbit, the 3D comes with a flash on the camera whereas the 3B is without one. Datasheet LinkGPSThe receiver is a 12 channel L1 only SiRF receiver. I was really hoping for a dual-constellation (GLONNASS capable) receiver on this device, as you can even find that on the iPhone 4S. It's scary to think that a professional mapper is running around with one less satellite constellation than a teenager checking into a coffee shop using FourSquare-- but I guess you could make the argument that it's not the quantity of satellites, it's the quality of processing. Or maybe there really is no excuse for this. It's time to get dual-constellations in this box-- it would literally make it a rockstar. 3.5G Modem/PhoneThe phone / modem equipment is standard on the 3D. I love how Trimble does not jump on the AT&amp;amp;T bandwagon and call HPSA+ hardware 4G. However, they probably should, as everyone else is doing it. Personally, If I were to purchase a new Juno, I would opt for the 3B, as the 3D device does not qualify as my daily driver phone-- it would have big shoes to fill from my Nexus S 4G. I'd rather pair the Juno 3B device with a Verizon MiFi for a few reasons:Cheaper cost of hardware $799 for 3B vs $1099 for 3D.I can use a Verizon MiFi to connect multiple devices.Field devices have a season, and I'd rather not carry the cost of an AT&amp;amp;T contract when I'm not using it.Lack of support. There's barely any documentation out there from Trimble on where/how to purchase a sim card, and what plan to get. This is unacceptable from a product management perspective-- but I digress. I'll get off of my soap box.BatteryThis is the best battery that I've seen in an MGIS device... ever. I used the unit on and off for a few weeks and only charged it once. Of course, the way a blogger uses a device is much different than the average field user. But lets just say that you'll easily pull a day + battery life with full usage of this device. The battery is huge. It's a 3060mAh Lithium-Ion Cell, which equates to a large, enduring power plant given the size of this device. Test PrefaceFor my tests, I really just tested the precision and the accuracy of the Juno. For such a low price point (under $1100.00 for the best model), I really wanted to get a feel for positional accuracy of this thing. Trimble specs it at 2-5 Real-Time with SBAS (WAAS in USA), and 1-3 Meters post-processed. I know from experience that Trimble is extremely conservative on their accuracy statements, the units will almost always outperform specifications.Test 1For my first test, I tested precision. Anyone can easily do this at home. Just bust out some measuring tape, lay it on the ground and take shots at predetermined values. For my test I set up for one minute on 0' and one minute on 10'. I measured using SBAS and post-processed. The results were surprisingly good.The Real-time SBAS was the best, yielding ~ 2.34' of error. Post-Processed was not far behindTest 2For my next test, I went out and collected a few NGS monuments to test the Accuracy of the device. Maybe I was a little hard on the Juno in my Modem section above, so to even the playing field, I decided to go heads up with my Nexus S 4G just to see how the GPS's performed against each other. In short order, I quickly found that my smartphone just can't even compare when it comes to accuracy. The Juno was hitting 3.6 feet away from the monument in Real-Time (with SBAS), whilst the Nexus S 4G was hitting 36 feet away from the monument-- thats a 10x difference. So let's level the playing field, Trimble has much less ground to cover in the smartphone game than smartphones have to cover in the precision GPS game.I hit up two NGS Monuments: Designations JOG and COMMITMENT near my house. I occupied each monument for 60 seconds and just placed the Juno directly on top of the monument. I then post processed the results. The Juno did not surprise me-- it hit the 3 - 3.2 ft spec consistently.What's even better was the 3-Dimensional accuracy of this receiver. You see when I test a GPS, I just don't test 2d performance or vertical performance-- I test 3-Dimensional performance, because we live in a 3D world. The Juno consistently hit within 4 - 5 feet in three-dimensional space during my tests. Below is the spreadsheet to prove it (see NGS Monuments).NGS Monument ResultsConclusionI believe that this is the best value in Mobile GIS right now. iPhones, Androids, and Windows Phone 7 devices using ArcGIS for Smartphones are on the verge of disrupting the Mobile GIS Low-End in hardware sales. This hardware release is a testament to that. Technology will get cheaper with smartphones, accuracy will improve, perhaps new positioning technology might come out left field and really disrupt the precision game-- you just never know these days.This device is the ultimate Emergency Response Hardware, hands-down. I happen to be judging from a purely consumer perspective. However, if a giant oil spill or flood were to happen I'd want a fleet of these devices (probably with the modem and ArcGIS Mobile) to survey the scene, and provide timely information to the people who need it most.Given the parlance of this technological time, It's extremely dangerous to label this device as a high-end phone-- lead with the GPS. Why do I muddy the water of my Juno review with these facts? Because the Juno is Trimble's low-end entrant. The 3d model that I've had my hands on is actually a phone. In a world on phones, Trimble really has a challenge. Its entrant has a price point of just under $1100 dollars, it isn't running Android, iOS, or Windows Phone-- its running Windows embedded,  and yes it still necessitates a stylus.But I believe that Trimble has a shorter distance to go in the phone world than smartphones have to go in the Precision Space. Esri (a close business partner of Trimble's) has already built a bridge into these ecosystems with their smartphone apps and api's. There will be a convergence. Mark my word, Dual-constellation receivers will be the norm on smartphones in the next years to come-- thus helping accuracy on this low-end platform. This is an opportunity. Perhaps the next itteration of this product doesn't need to be a box, it needs to be an app.If I got something wrong, or if you'd like to contribute to the conversation, please leave comments.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2012/06/04/trimble_juno_3_d_review/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e52352cb-3f72-4957-8be8-e8fe1b532958</guid><category>g_i_s</category><category>e_s_r_i</category><category>arc_g_i_s</category><category>iphone</category><category>trimble</category><category>android</category><category>gps</category><category>mobile_gis</category><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 05:12:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Google Glasses as GIS Tools</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Nick Bilton, from the NY Times recently posted an article about a new product from Google called Google glasses.In his article, he talks about how these glasses will use augmented reality to play location-based games, display advertisements, connect with friends, etc. What I found missing from this conversation and subsequent conversations around the web, was the perspective on how geospatial developers would be able to exploit the power of this new medium through an api.Wouldn't it be great if this could be used as a field tool to help us "literally visualize" the assets in our geospatial datasets?Imagine a first responder, ambulance driver, police officer being able to know for sure that the address they pulled up at is indeed the right one? What kind of information or data about this property would be useful for this first responder? Given the fact that we already have these E911 datasets, we could take it a step further by integrating them with this tool.Imagine integrating this tool with a BIM, and arming a firefighter with the ability to navigate through an area with poor to no visibility-- safely.How about utility companies? Surely it would be nice if they could drive right up to an asset, visualize it in real-time, and update the asset database more easily.What I'm speaking about already exists. However the tools that accomplish these tasks are in the form of Toughbooks strapped to the inside of a vehicle, or a pda that can be a hindrance during a critical moment that you would need both of your hands. The underlying datasets that these existing tools pull from already exist-- they are curated by Geospatial professionals in our field. In addition, one would assume that these glasses would integrate with the Maps API, which happens to be the most popular Google api in the world right now-- for which many organizations have already confidently embraced.The tools to exploit these datasets might change form factors one day; and I believe these Google Glasses are a good tool to bridge the gap between augmented reality and GIS.Cheers,Alex Mahrou&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2012/02/27/google_glasses_as_gis_tools/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e8c08d62-efe9-4786-a407-2444ebb9d983</guid><category>g_i_s</category><category>gps</category><category>lbs</category><category>augmented_reality</category><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 00:24:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The definition of dead...</title><description>&lt;p&gt;There has been much talk in the tech community about how Flash, (and to some extent Silverlight) is now dead. This is amid announcements from Adobe, that they are discontinuing support for flash mobile. The GIS community tends to adopt technology on the coattails of the greater tech communities' adoptions. Some talking heads in the greater tech community are proclaiming that Flash is dead! Silverlight is dead! Now as one would expect, some GIS talking heads are analogously shouting flex is dead! Silverlight is dead! The folks in the community who are shouting these things are usually GIS Entrepreneurs who have heavily-vested their incomes on custom (non-out-of-the-box) solutions.-- Not that there is anything wrong with that...I'll point you to a tweet from a tech podcaster/journalist that I follow, Joshua Topolsky, "Pronouncing something as dead, is usually a sign that it is very much alive."HTML5 is the future. It's non-proprietary, more foot-loose, and it will allow for much more flexibility when designing applications that run in the mobile space. However, Flex/Flash, and Silverlight are in the present-tense-- which is not in the past. Therefore, I would not call it dead. Stop calling things dead. It's cute, and you'll definitely get some attention for it. However it shows an utter ignorance as to how things are currently working in the present-tense. I seriously doubt that the Esri UC will be filled with HTML5-only apps. Get with the times man. You've saddled up on the "it's dead" tech bandwagon and tried to to apply its ridiculous principles to the present-tense in GIS. Those attending the Esri UC should be looking at the problems that are solved using GIS. It would be a shame if people were fixated on how current or hip the platform is that gets you there. These are the same dudes who are leading the no-sql, no-gis boutique movements to no-where.Esri's been very smart in their approach to the community talk of HTML5 and the future of their platforms. They have not proclaimed anything as dead, and they have seen that HTML5 is part of the future landscape.Many in the community cite Google as leading the charge for HTML5. Whilst Google is a huge backer of HTML5, there's a reality check-- In the PRESENT-TENSE a little Geospatial app called Street-View (not sure if you've heard of it) on Google Maps, still leverages Adobe Flash.This landscape is in-fact changing. There's a really good podcast by Directions Mag how far we have come, and what we might expect from HTML5.I look forward expanding my horizons in GIS by learning how to leverage/customize apps that run on HTML5 in the FUTURE. However I'm currently (Present-tense) building geospatial web applications that run on Adobe Flex. The environment fits my clients needs, and there is great support from a community of developers that's building widgets on top of this platform.My only point in writing this little post, is to hopefully arm folks with enough ammunition the next time they hear someone say "that's dead". There is a difference between the Past, Present, and Future. Don't believe all the hype. HTML5 is the future, however it has not gained a critical mass in Geospatial usage. Be proud of your Flex/Silverlight apps. They are allowing you to share information that helps to solve todays problems in the PRESENT-TENSE. So long as they continue to do this, there is no reason why you should abandon them. You'll never hear me proclaim that any technology is dead.-- It's always good to keep your options open, use tools that solve todays problems, and keep abreast of what's on the horizon.A very smart past co-worker of mine told me something that stuck with me years ago, "Never apply technology for technology's sake". Cheers,Alex&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://projected.xyz/2011/11/21/the_definition_of_dead_/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">01624e3a-15e3-40ba-a5aa-e2a606e84c56</guid><category>arc_g_i_s</category><category>flex</category><category>h_t_m_l5</category><category>silverlight</category><dc:creator>Alex Mahrou</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 00:02:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>